[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
foreign
good evening good day everyone I hope
you're all doing very well and uh thank
you for being on the 143rd episode of
the ask Abhijit show
I hope the image is good so here we are
uh so before we begin as always let me
see who all is there with us I can see
chiching Karthik Ayan vitamin protein
kitchen
kushal social
good evening
Clipper flipper Vladimir adityanat
ankushnath YK Mr Giga Chad of India
chiang's world yes 059
Eternal Light Shiva Prasad nikhil Nero
Saddam Hussein is here with
using khorana Aditi again Mona Lisa
Anthony Mack bharatpaksh the Colt God
Roshan Riker
Mr Nobody social wishes online
foreign
yesterday I apologize for yesterday
there were some technical issues there
was some lag and all that today I have a
whole different setup I have a different
Service uh internet service provider a
different Broadband different laptop new
laptop and all so hopefully things are
better things will go better today I
hope the image is clear I've tried to
replicate the same image as I had before
so uh so I hope everything goes fine
today right so with that said let us get
into the questions what questions do we
have today
um
okay let's take the first one by Amit
Amit says very C grade performance very
very secret performance by the Russian
army they were gaining ground attacking
but only by destroying cities and so on
so forth so it's about car cave it's
about kerson
so the the overall sentiment is that the
Russians are losing it's they're doing
very poorly and that's what many people
seem to be thinking and there is I mean
it makes sense to think that way because
the Russians withdrew from kharkiv the
Russians withdrew from carezone so
what's happening so let us revisit this
one more time
let's take a look at the map so somebody
was very kind enough to send me a good
map of Ukraine on Twitter I usually use
an interactive map but let's take a look
at this map I don't know who the person
is but thank you very much sir or ma'am
for sending this map this is a very good
color-coded map and it will help us
understand the thing better the
situation better so uh this is an older
map you can see that uh the Crimean
Republic is shown as part of Ukraine it
is no longer part of Ukraine it was
annexed by the Russians in 2014.
the four Crimean oblasts or Republic the
the four Ukrainian oblasts or republics
that have been annexed by Russia are her
son
Donetsk and luhansk right the four
Southeastern ones
now uh the situation is that the
Russians a few months ago withdrew from
kharkiv right kharkiv is the city over
here in the north they withdraw from it
the Widow from cargive and recently just
a few days ago they uh withdrew from
north of the Nipper River in the kherson
OR blast so they evacuated carouson City
for several months before this happened
for several weeks before this happened
and then they uh withdrew from uh the
right Bank of the diaper river which is
the north north west of the Kirsten
province that is what happened
right uh so what they did before the the
withdrew is they evacuated all the
russian-speaking people from that region
see the kherson region is Russian
majority
and that's why the Russians have annexed
it but they evacuated all the Russian
ethnicity people the russian-speaking
people from the region for several weeks
and only then they withdrew from the
region because they knew what the
ukrainians would otherwise do to the
Russian speakers because we know what
they've been doing to the Russian
speakers since 2014. so the Russians did
this first and then they withdrew from
that part of kherson Province and I had
said when the news first came in that
there are three possibilities three
possibilities of what's really happening
the first possibility is that NATO is
winning this is a proxy war between
Russia and NATO Ukraine is the proxy so
the first possibility is that NATO is
winning and Russia is losing that's why
they were thrown out of kharkave and
they were forced to evacuate from that
part of Herson right so if that is true
if this possibility is the correct
possibility if this is the right thing
then you will see that the ukrainians
will try to cross the river and try to
move into
the other part the Russian occupied part
of Herson province which is south of the
river niper and they may even try to
make a move on Crimea so if NATO is
winning if the Russians have been thrown
out then this is what's going to happen
but it's not happened thus far
so
what's the second possibility the second
possibility I said is that there are
negotiations going on secretly for a
ceasefire and the Russian withdrawal
from this part of kherson is maybe a
prerequisite for the ceasefire and maybe
something will happen during the G20
Summit or right after the G20 Summit
immediately after it well the G so G20
Summit came and went this week and
nothing was announced and nothing
there's been no move in that direction
either and the third possibility I said
is that the Russians are laying a nasty
trap for NATO so they will withdraw from
this Legion let the Ukrainian forces
NATO forces come into the kherson City
and then they will obliterate it well
even that has not happened the
ukrainians are not stupid they also
sense that there could be this sort of
nasty surprise waiting for them so they
have not moved into Carson City in big
big numbers yes they have taken the city
of course and so on their so-called
liberated the city and that's what's
happening so I had put fourth three
possibilities NATO winning is one second
is
ceasefire negotiations have happening in
secret and third nasty trap for NATO
well thus far we have seen nothing
happening neither possibility a nor
possibility B no possibility C so what
is happening
so what is happening and you know I am
sure there is a lot of anger in Russia
as well about
first of all the withdrawal from kharkiv
and secondly then this this new
withdrawal from north of the Naper River
in the kherson region I am sure there is
a great deal of anger and resentment
among the Russian population
and in in Russia when when you have a de
facto dictator who's ruling the country
this sort of resentment is very
dangerous it is very dangerous it can
lead to the downfall if of the leader Mr
Putin if he becomes deeply unpopular if
he is seen to have failed
and yet he willingly withdrew his forces
from kharkiv and he willingly withdrew
his forces from kherson so what's
happening
what's happening there is a fourth
possibility I believe that the Russians
are waiting for winter it's still not
winter if you look at the if you Google
the the weather in Kiev right now you
will see it's it's zero degrees or minus
minus one minus two thereabouts yeah so
it's it's late Autumn it's already
becoming really cold it's already
touching the zero degrees mark and going
into the minus degree negative
temperatures yes but it's not winter yet
when is winter really there
winter is really there in full force
when the ground freezes
when the rivers freeze over the rivers
don't necessarily able to freeze over
but the ground needs to freeze all the
muddy boggy patches of ground all over
Ukraine Ukraine is extremely flat it's
flat like a pancake there are no Hills
there are no mountains it's flat flat
flat and there are places where you have
mud There Are Places you have bog and
all that all that in the winter it
freezes it becomes solid I believe the
Russians are waiting for that to happen
and right now what they're doing is they
have pulled out their forces
from Kharkov kharkiv from Carson they
are re-configuring their forces there
they have also recruited more people and
all that and they are waiting for the
ground to freeze they are waiting for
General winter to make his arrival into
novor Russia into Ukraine and I believe
once that happens there will be a major
push forward military push forward the
Russian the Russian people will not
tolerate any perceived loss by the
Russian Armed Forces right
so it is a significant possibility in my
opinion
that the Russians are merely waiting
they they are they are withdraw this is
the Tactical withdrawal they are waiting
for the ground to freeze and then there
will be a major push forward so by mid
December perhaps you could see a major
upsurge in military activity and major
push forward by the Russian forces they
have until now withheld significant
portions of their military
the arm the the Air Force has hardly
been involved at all it is being kept in
reserve for the future big war
and there's a whole lot more to come
so I think there is a possibility number
four that in within a month's time maybe
in two weeks three weeks whenever the
ground freezes the Russians will push
forward big push forward you know
massive push forward and that could
essentially change the map of Ukraine
forever
and NATO knows that because how do why
do I say nato knows that I say this
because
let me put something on the screen
because of this
this is from The Washington Post it's
from November 5. today is November 20.
that's like two weeks ago the U.S
privately asks Ukraine to show its open
to negotiate with Russia yeah
so over here it's it's being said that
the encouragement is not aimed at
pushing Ukraine into the negotiating
table but ensuring it maintains that
moral how high ground in the eyes of
international backers and so on but the
Americans are asking Ukraine
to privately to show that it's open to
negotiate maybe there are negotiations
that are happening we don't know maybe
there are these things are not announced
until it's a faith accompli yeah so I
think there is a significant possibility
that the Russian withdrawal from kharkiv
from kherson Etc it's a tactical
withdrawal it's like a chess move in
which you know you pull back for a while
maybe sometimes you may even sacrifice a
pawn or a chest piece here and there and
then you do what you are really uh
planning to do so I think
I may be wrong of course but I think in
two to three weeks maybe by my
mid-December when the ground is totally
frozen you will see a major offensive
that will change the whole dynamics of
the war major Russian offensive so let's
see I'm putting this out in the open
let's see if I'm right let's see if I'm
wrong Time Will Tell Us by mid December
I think this could happen
or maybe by the latest by the end of
December I don't think the Russians will
wait once the ground is properly Frozen
I don't think they'll wait
they're gonna push so let's see if this
is this is this is the case and they
have the ability to overrun paths
significant portions of Ukraine in very
less time especially if the Air Force
gets involved in that case they can
annihilate the resistance from from the
NATO NATO backed Ukrainian proxy forces
so uh that is what could be in the
offing that that's what could come very
soon let's wait and watch and let's see
if I'm right or if I will be proven
wrong all right
okay next question
harsh Agarwal says do you think Trump
will come back as President of the U.S
I'm assuming and can India and Indians
really trust Donald Trump I heard in an
interview with a foreign U.S national
security advisor that if the Chinese
give him Assurance on vote civil side of
the Chinese what's my take I don't think
Donald Trump is a traitor to his country
siding with the Chinese means betraying
your own Nation I don't think Donald
Trump is that sort of a person obviously
he has business dealings worldwide
including with China what's wrong with
that I am sure the other side also has
plenty of people including at very high
position in high positions who have all
kinds of dealings with China
I think we know about that I'm not gonna
speak about it but I think you all know
what I mean
so uh it's perfectly fine to have legal
legitimate business dealings with
Nations like China with with Russia with
India with whoever else you want what's
wrong with that but I do not think that
Donald Trump will betray his nation in
in exchange for an assurance of votes
when I don't know I don't know what
interview you're talking about I'm not
I'm not sure which NSA you're referring
to but if somebody is
is saying
that Donald Trump will side with
with China
if the Chinese
give him assistance with votes you are
essentially saying that the Chinese are
capable of of interfering with the
electoral process of the U.S until now
they've been saying Russia now they are
saying that you are essentially
alleging that Donald Trump will betray
his country in exchange for for Chinese
interference elections I think there is
incredibly stupid if somebody has
actually said that I personally have not
heard heard about it so that's Point
number one
I don't think Donald Trump will betray
his Nation inside with China in exchange
for Chinese interference in the election
uh electoral uh process of the U.S okay
so that's number one uh do I think
Donald Trump will come back in 2024 or
Time Will Tell Us I think it's unlikely
I know it's it's not a popular thing to
say lots of Indians are are big fans of
Mr Trump I think it's unlikely that
Donald Trump will come back why do I say
this because he is an outsider in U.S
politics he came in as an outsider and
and
managed to secure the Republican
nomination for presidency in 2016. it
was a shock to the Republican party all
those although all the seasoned
politicians they all sound the same they
don't say they talk a lot without saying
anything Donald Trump came in and
grabbed the entire process by the throat
and he was very popular with the
Republicans with the with the population
the vote the the voters and that's how
he was able to win the Republican
nomination and then he was able to
defeat uh who was it Hillary Hillary
Clinton right
so he's an outsider there are people
within his own party who don't like the
fact that this businessman this business
tycoon came in and and shoved them all
aside and became so popular there are
plenty of in he has plenty of opponents
within his own party and secondly the
overall electoral system in the U.S
whether it's Republicans or whether it's
Democrats they they both hate him it's a
bipartisan uh dislike of Donald Trump
they don't want this sort of thing to
ever happen again that an outsider a
non-politician
manages to enter politics
and wins
it's bad for business
politics is deeply deeply linked to
business and money yeah it's it's bad
for business if if a non-politician
becomes president
so I Donald Trump we know he has already
announced his candidacy for the 2024 uh
Republican nomination for presidency
yeah and he has challenges like Ron
desantes and various other people you
know some new names may come up in the
in the future in the coming months yeah
uh but I think there's going to be a
significant amount of resistance from
within his party and even if he manages
to secure once again the Republican
nomination there could be I mean the
Democrats will will try to make life
hell for him yeah of course he is now
back on Twitter he hasn't tweeted yet he
Elon Musk has reinstated Donald Trump's
Twitter account which was canceled in
2020.
um so yeah that that's he is a very
entertaining person on Twitter and he
knows how to
keep people focused on him so he has a
lot of advantages that other politicians
don't have as a politician you need to
have personality
other politicians all look and sound the
same
and of course you need to know what
you're doing you need to understand the
issues that people are facing and you
need to be able to provide genuine
Solutions or you need to be able to
convince the people that you have the
solutions and you will be able to
implement those Solutions Donald Trump
has done that in the past
but yeah I think uh I think he faces
significant challenges when it comes to
the 2024 election firstly from within
his own party if he succeeds in that
then he will face uh I mean the entire
media in the U.S I would say that 90 of
the US media is controlled by the
Democrats and people public opinion is
easy to easy to sway through social
media and through the mainstream media
if you keep saying the same things over
and over and over again and not just one
person but the entire media Machinery
it's very easy to influence people's
minds people are people are very
gullible people don't understand things
unfortunately that's how it is so I
think it's difficult for Donald Trump
yeah so that's the point number two that
I think it will be very very hard for
him to come back uh can India and
Indians really trust him we can trust
Donald Trump to if he does come to power
in 2024 we can trust him to uh
uh to pursue his National interest any
any self-interest you can't trust him
beyond that
he he he's not going to serve India he's
going to if he does become president
he's
Duty will be to serve his Nation
America First like he says make America
great again that's always been his
campaign slogan that's always been his
platform is plank that I'm here to make
America great again
so if India
can
create that sort of relationship with
him in which we say that you know
we will help you make your country great
again what do you need from us
and what can we get in return that sort
of if we have that sort of relationship
and that sort of negotiating platform it
will work well
so we can trust him
to try and fulfill his campaign promises
to make America great again and you know
all those things you can't trust him to
to favor your nation if you want him to
favor your nation you have to give him
something in return that's how it goes
right
um
so to to that extent we can certainly
trust him
so that's what I think about this I
think he I do not believe that he is is
somebody who who will betray his nation
in favor of the Chinese yeah
the you know
that's I don't think so I don't believe
that at all secondly I think it will be
very hard for him to come back it will
be much harder than in 2016 and thirdly
we can trust him to want to fulfill and
to do his best to fulfill his campaign
promises if he's really re-elected and
if we if India can help him in that
aspect in that matter then it will be
mutually beneficial for India and the US
yeah but overall we know that he has
been of all the recent U.S presidents he
was the one who was the most favorably
inclined towards India
I mean if you talk about George W bush
if you talk about Barack Obama if you
talk about uh Mr Biden and if you talk
about Trump I mean these are the four
more recent ones the 20 21st century
presidents more or less yeah
so uh
so yeah he has been the one that was the
most favorable inclined among all of
these if you go back one more presidency
Clinton was very much Pro Pakistan right
Bill Clinton that I'm talking about so
Trump
would be very much open to negotiate
with India and work in in mutually
constructive and beneficial ways so that
in that sense it could be good for India
but I think Indians should not hope too
much that he will be re-elected it's
going to be a hard climb for him
um he has already been demonized to the
High Heavens or to the to the depths of
Hell by the American Media but of course
he was able to win the Twitter uh the
Twitter uh poll whether he should be
reinstated or not so that he does seem
still to have a lot of popularity he
still is the biggest
face in the Republican Party
so he has some advantages but he also
has a
steep climb ahead of him so that's where
it is
and let's see how it goes but they
should always keep our options open
says what's your take on the handshake
between Prime Minister Modi in modern
day Mao of China is there going to be
some normalcy in the relationship
between India and China Monmouth says
finally shook hands of the G27 in Bali
what future does do in Dutch India China
relations hold in the upcoming years
look
let me say this all over one more time I
I will keep saying this India cannot
trust China the Chinese are a hegematic
expansionist imperialist power right
that's that's the core focus of the
Chinese Communist party to make China
the number one nation in the world at
the expense of everybody else they don't
want a bipolar World they don't want a
multi-polar world they want a unipolar
world with China at the center China is
the Imperial power everybody else is
there was all everybody else comes and
and pays tribute to China that is the
envisioned World Order
and that's their world that's that's
that's the kind of world they would like
to create now they have faced setbacks
setbacks of late the coronavirus crisis
has been a disaster for China it's still
a big big problem in China they still
have the zero lockdown policy and all
that
so they're Ascend their rise to
ascendancy has been greatly delayed
they still hope that they will replace
the us as the sole superpower but it's
still just a hope uh the belt and Road
uh initiative which was supposed to be
the vehicle that takes China there has
kind of stalled but they would like to
re restart it with the help of bricks
plus plus Brix plus expanded bricks and
all that yeah so that's the situation
yeah
um
so if
so it is also in good for India if there
is a new emerging world order we don't
want a Chinese dominated unipolar world
order we want a multi-polar world order
a multiple world order in which there
are multiple info sources
centers of power multiple polls India
China Russia the US the U.S led block
the the the Western Bloc and so on maybe
we would like some nations in Africa
also to step up if it's possible to free
them from uh Western Colonia
colonization and all that so India seeks
a multi-polar world
and the how do you how do you make such
a multipolar world come about well the
most important uh factor or the most
important vehicle that India can use for
creating a multiple overall order would
be bricks bricks plus because now more
than a dozen Nations have
stated that they want to join brics many
nations have actually applied officially
Indonesia applied this week at the G20
Summit to join brics
um
other nations have also applied so
bricks is a is a block that's going to
expand it's going to be bricks plus it
will still be called bricks we cannot
keep on adding letters of the alphabet
to it but it's going to be called bricks
Plus or bricks plus plus Whatever It Is
by 2025 2026 you could have maybe five
six more uh Nations that are members of
bricks maybe more
we will see how it goes the Saudis want
to join so G20
we have this G20 Summit right G20 has
been hijacked by the US in the G7
Nations if you look at the wording of
the final statement of the G20 Summit
it's you can see there's so much
references to Russia and Ukraine and War
which has nothing to do with the other
nations
so it's been hijacked by G2 by the by
the G7 Nations especially by the US the
g7s are all U.S Versailles I keep using
this word vasal but it's something that
you will see lots of other major
Publications also starting to use
nowadays all right so G20 has been
hijacked by the US I mean what business
does does uh Ursula of Wonderland have
been being being at the G20 Summit the
EU is not a member of G20 individual
nations are members of G20 there are 20
Nations
and yet all these things are imported
into into G20
and so on so
the core nations of j20 especially the
Eastern Nations the Asian Nations I
I can assure you they do not like this
they do not like their G20 organization
being co-opted and hijacked in this
manner yeah they also have their own
national interests to pursue they would
like there to be more trade more inter
operationality more cooperation between
especially the so-called Global South
and the Eastern Nations so for that they
have asean they also have other things
as well so the focus will now move more
towards that and they will also now want
to be part of part of bricks because
brics excludes brics has nothing to do
with the G7 Nations or NATO or the EU or
the US so that's where they will feel
more comfortable that's what they see
enormous potential for growth and
progress so that's why Brix is becoming
more and more attractive to these
nations but brics is a non-starter if
the two major Nations within brics then
their leaders can't even talk to each
other
we have these tensions with China the
undemarkated border the the Chinese
occupied Tibet which they occupied in
the 1950s
and the Chinese claims on Indian
Territory the in the recent military
clashes the galwan clashes or the other
salami slicing tactics of China trying
to encroach here in their all the time
constantly
this is a major point of friction
it could even lead to a war in the
future if this situation continues brics
is a non-starter brics cannot be a
viable organization
and India understands that the Chinese
also understand that and that's why it
looks like there's been some diplomacy
behind the scenes
and it was agreed that India and China
the leaders will meet I'll meet briefly
just for a couple of minutes you know
just a brief greeting some pleasantries
a few words exchanged and that's it in
full view of the world in public at the
G20 uh official dinner whatever that
event was so it that was a message to
the Nations that want to join bricks the
things that we can make things work
you don't need to worry about it right
because it is good for India if brics
expands and like-minded Nations join
it's also good for China they would like
to use bricks for their own purposes of
course they would like to restart the
Bri the built-in Road thing yeah and
they could use bricks to kick-start it
but it's also good for India that more
influence and more power comes towards
brics rather it's it's all the entire
world is right now under the strangled
hold of the West
everything the so-called rules-based
world order the whims-based world order
so we would like to see a parallel
system emerging
which is more in our favor of course the
Chinese will be involved of course the
Russians are involved we can trust
Russia India and Russia have no friction
points whatsoever
but China is the problem that Russia and
India don't trust but we will have to
find a way to work together and that's
the reason why the handshake happened
it doesn't mean things are going to be
normal
I would still be surprised if the
Chinese agree to actually uh
finally uh demarcate the India Tibet
border that entire process will take few
a few years but it's never started they
have this endless rounds of meetings
between India and China in which nothing
no progress ever happens the Chinese are
doing this deliberately they're
deliberately stalling this they have no
interest
in demarcating the Border well I think
India will have to negotiate with the
Chinese hard India will have to play
hardball that if you do want this thing
to go forward bricks if you do want
normal scene bricks if you want bricks
to be a viable organization these are
the non-negotiable conditions
so maybe there is there is some progress
perhaps happening in that matter we
don't know negotiation diplomacy always
happens in secret negotiations always
happen in secret maybe something is
happening maybe something is not we
don't know assuming it's happening we
hope that things can get better
but we have to always remember that we
cannot trust China
right so maybe things are getting better
maybe India China relations will improve
but even if they do improve we have to
always be very
China is much more powerful militarily
and economically we have to ensure that
we catch up with them so that's got to
be the main focus India ideally needs
another 20 years without any major
conflict major major war then we can
deal with the world yeah so that is our
focus and Bricks will help us get in the
go in the direction
if we can maintain some kind of normalcy
even fake normally with China it will be
great next 20 years so that's what's
happening that is the future of India
China relations there could still be
what who knows if the Chinese so decide
India will not initiate any War
but uh if the Chinese so decide if Xi
Jinping and his Communist Party minions
so decide if the then there could be
something but hopefully there will be
more normalcy and and less friction that
would be good for the whole world I'm
sure the Chinese also understand this so
let's see how it goes but I think things
could get better
and let's hope so
okay three questions Rishi says India
just took over the G20 presidency yes
our government has hinted that the next
Summit is to be held in Srinagar
Pakistan is expected to Make Some Noise
We Will face some real problems in
hosting it in Sri Lanka Srinagar is a
geopolitically beneficial for us to host
it there manmad says G20 Summit 2023 is
most likely to be held in jnk Pakistan
is a nobody but what significance will
this act have upon China is China also
occupies a big part of that region of
India
the raghav says India is planning to
keep G20 made of Commerce ministers in
Kashmir what do you think will be the
geopolitical consequences of the same
okay so um most likely so even I've been
hearing this for the past few months
that maybe the next G20 Summit or some
part of it some portion of it will be
held in Kashmir maybe in ladakh maybe in
Srinagar somewhere else but in Kashmir
right
in Jammu and Kashmir so what does this
mean so Pakistan like you say is a
nobody Pakistan doesn't matter they can
they can howl to the heavens they can
protest they can complain doesn't make
any difference there's nothing they can
do about this right
so if India holds this Summit or some
portion of it in Kashmir jamun Kashmir
or in ladakh or some portion of that
region what does it mean what what is
the what are we doing what do we mean
what are we what are the signals that we
are sending and to whom are we sending
those signals the first signal that
India will be sending is that Jammu and
Kashmir
and ladakh are integral and inalienable
parts of India
that's the first thing and this signal
is essentially being sent to two
forces for two Nations China
and the US and the West
the West is essentially all controlled
and owned by the U.S The Americans
portray Jammu and Kashmir and ladakh as
disputed territory right the Americans
have been doing this for the past 60 70
years they portrayed as a disputed
disputed territory so if India holds the
summit there
it's an assertion to the Americans that
this is Indian Territory and then the
Americans will also have to come and
attend so if they do come and attend it
means they're ascending and they're
agreeing to the fact that this is Indian
Territory symbolically yeah they might
not say it in those words but they are
coming to jnk or ladakh in
being part of the G20 Summit there which
means that they are on Indian Territory
and they just by being there they are
symbolically recognizing the fact the
same goes to China the Chinese portray
jnk
Etc and all that as a disputed territory
the Chinese occupy a part of jnk the
shaksgam valley yes
so uh
which was a part of Pok in the
pakistanis then illegally gave that
portion of of ladakh to the Chinese the
shaks gam Valley region the so the
Chinese are in occupation of our
territory not just accessing but also
the valley of course they also occupy
oxygen and they portray the entirety of
jnk and ladakh and all that as disputed
territory so if we hold the G20 Summit
there they will also the Chinese will
also have to come the Xi Jinping will
have to come right and attend the summit
and if he does that it's a de facto
symbolic recognition of the fact that
this is Indian Territory
he may not say it but that's how it goes
so it is going to be a geopolitically
a big statement and and symbolism that
this is Indian Territory and the whole
world now comes here and recognizes the
fact so if we do it which we should it
will be great
so that's the reason why if it's going
to happen it's going to happen it's
going to happen in in wherever it is
wherever the final decision is taken if
it is Srinagar great wonderful
so the question is uh that's why it is a
it's a good thing it will be
geopolitically beneficial for us for us
to host it there uh what significance
will this higher act have up in China
like I said that's what it will mean for
China as well it will be a statement to
them and the fact that they do come and
attend means means that they are also
recognizing the fact this is part of
Indian Territory
um so that's what it is now what about
the security situation will there be any
security security problems well if there
is any security problem if there is any
potential security risk that risk will
only come from Pakistan because it's
right next door it occupies part of jnk
the and also right which is part of so
that is illegally occupied by Pakistan
and they have this history of of uh
fomenting terrorism in jnk
so if there is anything whatsoever which
could happen
terrorism or any security issue it can
only be via Pakistan and obviously the
pakistanis will be forewarned they'll be
told if anything goes wrong doesn't
matter who does it we're going to blame
you and we're gonna make you pay the
price for it
so that that's a guarantee
so the pakistanis will know that when
this big G20 meeting Summit is happening
if anything whatsoever happens even if
it's not your fault we're gonna blame
you
so I'm sure they will be made to behave
and uh because see this this government
knows how to make Pakistan behave before
2014 there were terrorist attacks in
India almost every week
there's this whole list you can find on
various websites including Wikipedia
dozens hundreds of terrorist attacks in
India
before 2014. every week almost every day
in some part of India after 2014
everything ends everything stopped
because this government has a very hard
line policy against terrorism of course
you have one or two incidents like the
URI attack which was Avenged brutally
and then there was the other thing as
well so then so the pakistanis were made
to understand that we're going to take
very severe action against you the
surgical strikes in the Bala Court
airstrike were two examples of that and
we can escalate it much further
so the pakistanis know that they can
play with fire so I think it will go off
safely securely if anything happens the
pakistanis will have to be will be made
to play a very very heavy price for it
so I'm sure they will not do any
nonsense any Mischief so that's about
the uh possibility of the G20 Summit the
next one the 2023 G20 Summit happening
in maybe Srinagar maybe somewhere in jnk
that'll be great I think we should do
that
Akshay says Saudi Crown Prince Salman
Muhammad bin Salman's actions in recent
developments like expressing interest to
join brics giving special waiver like
removing police verification
requirements for India and for Saudi
visa for Indians and other military and
strategic cooperation with India and
wanting to get away from the Western
Bloc are we seeing Saudi Arabia as an
important player of the current
geopolitical world order very good
question very good question let's take a
look at the maps now I don't have a
separate map for Saudi Arabia so we will
go to the the map that I usually that I
always use let's take a look at Saudi
Arabia from the perspective of geography
so we uh India is here as we all know
yeah in the center of the screen you go
westwards you have the Arabian Peninsula
our nearest neighbor Maritime neighbor
is Oman then you have Yemen and if you
go further west you have Saudi Arabia uh
after crossing the UAE
so Saudi Arabia is not really very far
from us it's obviously a very it's the
world's largest uh producer if I'm not
mistaken of
petroleum products oil gas all that
mainly oil yes and that's why it is
prosperous and that's why it is
geopolitically incredibly important and
significant and that's why the Americans
have so much of an interest in Saudi
Arabia so this entire nation was carved
out of the chaos in in the in the
aftermath of the so-called first world
war which was which was the first
European tribal War yes and this this
nation-state was established by the this
kingdom was established by the British
uh and later on after the the decline of
the British Empire in the in the
transference of power from London to
Washington the Americans became the
major patrons of Saudi Arabia and they
have propped up uh this this dynasty the
house of Saud and they are the major
beneficiary they have been the major
beneficiaries of the of oil from this
region now the Americans are a major oil
producer through fracking through Shale
oil all that
so uh and yet Saudi Arabia is a major
major Nation because it is it
contributes a significant uh amount of
the oil that is consumed globally
and it has a very big say in the oil
prices the amount of production that it
does is has a direct impact on the oil
prices in the world it is obviously the
major nation in the OPEC plus Group
which is the cartel of petroleum
exporting countries now India and Saudi
Arabia the past six seven years ever
since Mr Modi came to power the
relations between Indian Saudi Arabia
ever since have been excellent Mr Modi
has made it a point
to ensure that India and Saudi Arabia
and other nations in the Gulf region
have excellent relations right uh even
the UAE even Oman India even has a
couple of military bases if I'm not
mistaken let's not talk about it here
but yes we have excellent cooperation
with Oman with the UAE excellent
relations and with Saudi Arabia and the
Saudis are most likely if I'm not
mistaken India's number one number two
uh supplier of of uh oil yes
now recently what happened is uh before
the midterm elections uh inflation was
rising in the U.S uh gasp gasoline
prices were had risen significantly and
Joe Biden requested the Saudis to ramp
up oil production so that the prices
will go down and he will win the
election he even visited Saudi Arabia
but the sound is refused and they cut
down instead of increasing oil
production they cut oil production by
two percent which caused
a certain amount of surging certain
percentage increase in the in the oil
prices worldwide which is something The
Americans
I can assure you are greatly annoyed
about that is a go that is a Bad Thing
from the perspective our vasal state is
refusing to obey our orders what on
Earth is happening that's not good
from their perspective so that is a red
mark against Muhammad bin Salman from
the American perspective now Muhammad
bin Salman is saying that he wants to
join brics
that essentially for the Americans is
like there was all state saying that I
will now no longer obey you and I will
go and join the enemy camp that's
essentially what it means from the U.S
perspective that is a very dangerous
game that Muhammad bin Salman is playing
he's a very brave man and clearly he he
wants to win away his Nation from the
U.S influence
the the thing is this today there are
U.S troops on Saudi territory more or
less permanently stationed there you can
look it up what the numbers are where
the U.S military bases are in this
Southeast they buy significant
quantities of U.S Weaponry every year
that's how these are one of the top five
military budgets in the world if I'm not
mistaken I think the top five one it's
in the top five and they exclusively buy
U.S weaponry
so it's heavily dependent on the US from
that perspective it's a U.S client State
it's a U.S puppet state it's a U.S visal
state it's been that for a very long
time now Muhammad bin Salman wants to
take his Nation out of the clutches of
the Empire of the superpower and these
are all steps that he is taking in the
direction not obeying the U.S dictat to
ramp up oil production industries
cutting oil production that is a sign of
rebellion then expressing his intent his
willingness
his desire to join brics that is an even
bigger Act of rebellion yes
in this great closeness with India uh
giving various waivers to Indians for
for acquiring Saudi visas no more
there's no more any need for police
verification yeah so these are all steps
that bring the two Nations closer now
India is a nation that the U.S would
want to make their visality but India is
still fastly refused that we will not
bow to your dictates and we will not
you know become another Japan so India
has an independent foreign policy the
Saudis want to create an independent
policy foreign policy and that's what we
are seeing that these these steps are in
that direction
if the Saudis
succeed if Muhammad bin Salman succeeds
in taking Saudi Arabia out of the
clutches of the Empire or even partially
out of the clutches and become a member
of brics and if he succeeds in surviving
this transition period this pivot
then Saudi Arabia could become a
significantly important player in the
Middle East and in the overall
geopolitical world order it's it's a
difficult thing to do why is it
difficult because brics before Saudi
Arabia Iran has applied to join brics
if you study some history you will
realize that Saudi Arabia and Iran are
essentially like enemies they have a
very fraught relationship they have a
very hostile relationship Saudi Arabia
and Iran these are more or less enemy
Nations
so if Saudi Arabia has to join brics
they will have to make some kind of
peace with Iran it's possible but it's
complicated
yeah
so that's one obstacle in the way but I
am sure if India and China can possibly
perhaps make things work I am sure Saudi
Arabia Iran can also possibly perhaps
make things work but the main problem is
the overlord the United States the
Empire the superpower
will Muhammad bin Salman succeed
in
achieving
this transition this pivot to the east
he would like to become part of the East
the Eastern Bloc not the Western block
the will the Americans allow him to do
this
I can assure you the Americans will
throw everything we'll use every lever
every asset that they have at the
disposal
to stop Muhammad bin Salman from
transitioning from pivoting to the east
you will I I am pretty sure very soon
you will start seeing all kinds of
articles in the English-speaking media
the global media about how
bad and brutal and unjust of a ruler
Muhammad bin Salman is how undemocratic
he is what sort of
atrocities are being done in Saudi
Arabia against lgbtq plus plus people
what is the the the situation the
position of women in Social Society how
downtrodden it is
and how despotic and brutal and evil of
a dictator Muhammad Salman is obviously
the Jamal khashoggi case is there they
can always bring that out right
I can sense this
coming
very soon if Muhammad bin Salman
persists in steering his Nation
eastwards
so it will start like that and then they
will use every other means of the
disposal including regime change
so I would say that if Muhammad Salman
is
determined to do this he must have done
some very tough and hard calculations
and he must have come to the conclusion
that he is in a position to actually
succeed maybe try and do this and they
will obviously have to look out for his
own personal safety
yeah
so it's a it's a very bold move that he
is making
it is a very dangerous thing that is
doing going up against the the overlord
and it could be very dangerous for me we
know what happens to U.S puppets who
turn their backs in the U.S and try to
become independent Iraq tried to do that
they tried to suddenly
create their own uh
independent foreign policy yeah
that's what Saddam Hussein tried to do
you know we know what happened to him
and there are many more examples
so uh
so yeah and I even hear that Xi Jinping
is due to visit Riyadh very soon maybe
in a week maybe in a month or so yeah
he's scheduled to visit Riyadh so yeah
that could be a move in that direction
that Saudi Arabia wants to become part
of brics and since China is the major
the number one nation in the brics group
uh he will have to run it past Fijian
ping so maybe that's what's happening
yeah so Xi Jinping is personally going
to visit Riyad the Xi Jinping usually
doesn't travel much he recently went to
went to Bali now he's going to
imminently soon visit Riyadh so there
will be something happening there
so and then Saudi Arabia will have to
make make good with with Iran in some
way you know find a working relationship
a way of cooperating a way of listening
the tensions and so on so yeah it's a
complicated situation it's a complicated
scenario that we're witnessing Global
geopolitics right now is a very
complicated and there's a whole lot of
realignment happening but overall if uh
If Mohammed bin Salman is able to
somehow successfully pull this off then
Saudi Arabia will become a major
addition to the Eastern Bloc to the
brics block and it could become a major
player in in geopolitics but it is a
very dangerous thing
the Middle East has been in crisis for
decades it's all being
the the strings are all being pulled
from the West they have created this
artificial lines of conflict of tensions
sectarian tensions National tensions and
all that and they could pull off
something else
so you could see things getting really
bad in the Middle East maybe next year
this year is the year of the Ukraine war
maybe 2023 will be the year of tensions
and crisis in the Middle East
I may be wrong maybe maybe I'll be right
let's see how 2023 goes I think 2023 the
focus will be on the Middle East and on
Saudi Arabia and on brics and not so
much on Ukraine let's see how it goes
okay the next question is by Daniel
Nicholson the U.S Secretary of Treasury
Janet Yellen released a statement that
India could buy as much oil from Russia
as it wants along the lines of the price
cap mechanism mechanism while somebody
from the Indian side said that we do not
have to follow the price cap regulations
how is this shaping the new consumer
seller relations between India and
Russia and is the US resigned to Indian
adamancy or crude oil procurement from
Russia so yes the Americans were
insisting that see this price cap we
don't know what it is it's not been
announced yet maybe it will be announced
to you know in a week maybe two weeks by
definitely in December by December uh by
mid-December whenever it is announced it
will be soon so they want to impose a
price cap on Russian oil they want to
decide what is the highest price at
which the Russians can sell their oil
yeah and they want India they were
saying that they want India to abide by
the American price cap on Russian oil
means don't pay more than this much
amount to Russians to the Russians for
the oil you purchase from them India
said no now the Amer in India kept
saying no we will not do this we will
buy oil from Russia at discounted rates
and and it's it's between India and
Russia it's nothing to do with the US
you will not dictate to us what we do
that's what India's position has been
throughout now the Americans are saying
okay
India does not have to abide by with the
price cap go buy as much as you want but
the problem is this
India does not have a fleet of oil
tankers India for the past 70 years has
not bothered to invest in a major Fleet
of oil super tankers which means that
India for more than 90 percent of its
oil imports has to depend on oil tankers
ships that belong to other nations
now
whenever you are doing this
you need what's called insurance and
there are some other things as well
and the Americans in this insurance
thing all of that is controlled by the
West
so whenever you have this oil shipment
coming through you need to uh acquire
insurance for it for whatever reason if
the if something goes wrong you will be
reimbursed the money if there's an
accident if the oil tanker is diverted
if somebody else if some Pirates steal
it or whatever whatever can go wrong if
something goes wrong and you don't
receive the oil then it will be
reimbursed that's why you buy insurance
the insurance providers are all Western
and if India goes ahead with this
the West will not be willing to ensure
these oils applies to India
and if there is no insurance then the
the oil will not be available
of course India can do some
circumvention of this
um
you know there are some Shadow Way
tankers available that don't belong to
any Nation then which can be acquired
without any insurance and all that but
it's much more high risk it's risky so
because India has not invested in its
own National Fleet of oil super tankers
that's why India is now facing this
conundrum
so the thing is okay you buy oil at
whatever price you want but we will not
ensure your oil supplies so you will not
be able to use
Western tankers or whatever so it's
they're trying to make things very
difficult for India
yeah so that's the situation India is in
right now so what does India do about
this do the Russians have enough tankers
to send to India but even if something
happens in India will lose money here or
do we cooperate with the Chinese will
the Chinese be willing to cooperate so
that's the kind of situation India is
facing right now
so India and Russia want to trade
without any external interference India
wants to buy I think if I am not
mistaken Russia is now the number two
number three supplier of oil to India
maybe the number one I'm not sure
it was not even in the top ten but now
it's in the top three that's how much
oil India is uh buying from Russia which
has been the lifeline for Russia yeah
and that's how the Russians have been
able to ensure that they don't become
they don't have to go back begin to
China and that's why the Russians are
still in India
genuinely independent nation the Chinese
have not been able to make Russia their
visa state
because of the Indian
purchases of enormous amounts of Russian
oil now this situation is around the
corner
so India will have to find a solution to
that
so that's where we are so India will
insist that it's going to buy oil at
whatever price it decides or it
negotiates for the Russia the Americans
are known to to dictate
they they have no right to dictate to us
what price cap to use and all that but
now this new spanner has been thrown in
the works so let's see in what direction
things go but yeah it's it's complicated
right now and India will have to find a
solution to this problem
okay vinu says please tell about the new
South North Korean missile test is it
aimed at Japan or the US is North Korea
planning a new nuclear test right I
think two or three days ago the North
Koreans uh tested a ballistic missile
an intercontinental ballistic missile in
ICBM so what's the definition of an ICBM
I think it's a missile it's a ballistic
missile that has a range of more than I
don't know 6000 kilometers seven
thousand kilometers I'm not sure what
exactly it is it's a missile that's able
to
you that you can fire from from one
continent and you can hit a different
continent with it it's a missile with an
extended range minimum I would say five
thousand kilometers most likely I would
say that in ICM BM from my perspective
should have a range of at least eight
thousand kilometers that's what I would
that's what that's how I would classify
a missile as an ICBM anyhow the uh North
Koreans recently tested like two or
three days ago a new missile they have
been testing lots of missiles short
range missiles but this latest test was
that of an ICBM so it was an ICBM with a
looping
trajectory
it Rose about six thousand kilometers
plus above the surface of the Earth and
it splashed down in the sea let's take a
look at the map as always
where's the map
let's put the map on the screen
so let's go to Korea we have South Korea
you have North Korea yeah as you can see
West oh sorry east of North Korea you
have the Sea of Japan and then you have
Japan itself
so uh
the missile I think
uh it splashed down in the ocean
approximately
um
once again approximately a thousand
kilometers away from where it was
launched
so it splashed down its its impact in
the ocean was at approximately a
thousand kilometers from the point of of
uh from where it was launched and it
Rose about six thousand plus kilometers
above the surface of the Earth so if you
do the simple you know calculations
mathematical calculations it is it is
basically uh apparent that the range of
the missile is in excess of 10 000
kilometers
so this ballistic missile seems to be an
ICBM an intercontinental ballistic
missile one that is capable
of targeting the United States so let's
see what is the distance from let's say
the Korean Peninsula to let's say
California
it's about 9 600 kilometers
and and so this missile definitely has a
range of more than 10 000 kilometers
some Publications are saying that it has
a range of about 15 000 kilometers in
that case it would be the Hua song 17
missile which is an enormous missile
it's a two-stage missile if I'm not
mistaken with liquid fuel so liquid fuel
missiles need to be prepared because
liquid fuel is is hard it has to be kept
at a very low temperature and so on so
it's a liquid fuel missile with two
stages it's an enormous beside maybe the
largest missile in the world with a
range of about 15 000 kilometers in case
it isong seven that was tested
so these ICBM tests are only aimed at
the US
because if you want to Target Japan you
can use an intermediate range or short
range ballistic missile or a cruise
missile I'm not sure the Korean North
Koreans have Christmas sets but they do
have ballistic missiles of short and
medium ranges so you don't need to test
a 15 000 kilometer range missile if you
want to Target Japan so it's clear that
the target is the US and it's a message
that they are sending to the US that we
that your entire nation is within range
of our ballistic missile so this new
missile test in case it was that 15 000
range 15 000 kilometer range missile it
was aimed at the United States
uh obviously these these missiles can
also be used to Target China
so that's always something that we have
to keep in mind that
look North Korea is a Chinese client
State let's understand that it is a
nation it's a regime it's a dictatorial
regime that is propped up by the Chinese
if you study the history of the of the
Korean War and all that whatever ensure
after that it was essentially a conflict
between the Western Blog the U.S led
block and the USSR LED block at the time
China was very close to the USSR so the
Russians the Soviets assisted China in
this conflict in Korea and uh so that's
that's how this uh Peninsula the Korean
Peninsula was was partitioned between
North Korea and South Korea that's what
the that's what the English-speaking
Empire does everywhere it goes Northern
Ireland southern Ireland India Pakistan
the the fragmentation of the Indian
subcontinent the partition of the Korea
Korean nation and so on
uh and South Korea is a is a U.S client
State it's a U.S basal State it's under
permanent U.S occupation so North Korea
is a Chinese
it's a Chinese client State and this uh
missile test this ICBM test was aimed at
the U.S it was aimed at sending a
message to the U.S
and it's essentially a Chinese sock
puppet that the Chinese are telling the
U.S that we have multiple ways of
targeting you
now is the uh is North Korea planning a
new nuclear test so if I recall
correctly the North Koreans have done I
think six nuclear tests thus far in the
past I don't know a decade or so right
and uh it is I heard that they may be
getting ready for a new seventh nuclear
test it's possible
so we don't quite know if it happens I'm
sure they will it will be announced with
great Fanfare on North Korean media and
we will come to know about it and
obviously if you have uh tracking
stations you can you can detect the
seismic signature of a nuclear test and
you can actually even calculate the
yield of the nuclear device and so on so
uh once it happens we will know it I
believe they could possibly be getting
ready for a new nuclear test obviously
if you're testing ballistic missile you
should also show that you are capable of
you have nuclear weapons that you can
use as Warheads for those missiles so
it's possible that a new nuclear test
may be in the offing maybe sometime soon
let's see let's wait and watch and we
will know
okay says Rising tensions between two of
NATO's biggest militaries are driving
fears of the first war between between
two NATO alliance members what will be
the USS or NATO's rule if a war begins
between Greece and Turkey
this is a flash point that most people
are not paying attention to right now
let's take a look at the map
where's the map over here
okay let's see we know where India is we
know how to orient ourselves Go West
West West West West West West go to the
Mediterranean region and that's where
you have turkey and Greece
so what's happening here
so Greece and Turkey have a very nasty
history a history that goes back to the
ottoman occupation of the Anatolian
Peninsula the entirety of Anatolia which
is the major major portion of turkey the
peninsula region between the Black Sea
and the Mediterranean this region is
called Anatolia for the past 3000 or so
years ago it was Greek
the city of Troy is on the western coast
of Anatolia on the Aegean Sea and so on
then the Turks occupied Anatolia
gradually beginning about I don't know
what 800 years or so ago yeah they were
fleeing from the great armies of the
great Mongol conqueror Genghis Khan and
that's why they came south from Central
Asia and they entered Anatolia and they
entered European history essentially and
then this slowly conquered parts of
Anatolia and then they conquered the
whole of Anatolia and eventually the
Ottoman Empire that conquered parts of
Europe as well it was a very large
empire yeah so that's a history and
Greece was under ottoman occupation for
a significant period of time the Greeks
don't like turkey for obvious reasons
for obvious reasons I'll not go into the
history if you are interested look it up
I think it makes sense what kind of
atrocities would have been perpetrated
on the Greeks yeah
uh so even in the late 19th century the
city of Thessaloniki was part of the
Ottoman Empire
it was then called Salonika
uh and then there were many wars between
Greece and Turkey including in the 1920s
the Turkish war of independence in which
Mustafa was able to evict the Western uh
Coalition out of turkey and and create
an independent nation of turkey so
Greece and Turkey they have this Blood
hatred this Blood enmity
many Turks actually have Greek ethnicity
and the reason for that if you want to
know please study it yourself yeah I'll
not go into that right now
no need to create controversies
unnecessarily at this point
so Grace and turkey are enemies
understand that Greece and Turkey are
actually mortal enemies who find
themselves both part of NATO strangely
enough so that's the thing which I keep
talking about the real major power in
Western Europe
in southern Europe is the US
that's the real name major major power
in Europe in in especially uh East uh
western and southern Europe it's the U.S
that's a major power they have kept this
continent more or less peaceful
obviously they have done some Mischief
here and there you can look it up
so that's why these two eliminations are
part of this U.S led Coalition NATO
now what is happening so now why are we
seeing these tensions between these two
Nations right so that's the history now
now Greece and Turkey are now
becoming more and more this this
relationship is becoming more and more
tense tensions are rising what is
exacerbating the rising of the tensions
that we have to understand something
must be happening right that is causing
the tensions to rise what is happening
is the question and who is causing this
to happen let's see
let us see let's put something uh so
before I I tell you why the tensions are
rising let me show you an example of the
rising tensions this is just this week
Mr erdogan was in Bali for the G20
Summit and he threatened Greece like I
said yesterday erdogan repeats straight
against Greece during G20 the Turkish
president warned the neighboring country
Greece that he could invade it certainly
one night
what a thing to say
what a thing to say huh
he told reporters that turkey can come
suddenly one night and that its neighbor
should mind its place and remember the
history remember the history remember
what we did to you what we have done to
you for centuries
mind your place
and we can come suddenly one night any
night we can come and things will go
really bad for you so now let me explain
why these tensions are rising why is Mr
erdogan so so angry
let's understand
here is one example
do you see this turkey condemns U.S
decision to lift Cyprus arms embargo
let's understand where is Cyprus let's
go back to the map
where is Cyprus and what what is what
does Cyprus have to do with all this
so Cyprus is this island here
you see this island here it is west of
Lebanon and south of turkey Anatolia
this island has historically been a
Greek island during the Ottoman
occupation
there were lots of people who were
converted to the ottoman religion and
Northern Cyprus is now in the 1970s the
Turks invaded the island of Cyprus and
they currently occupy the northern let's
say quarter or third of the island there
is this dashed line that you see over
here on the map
it's it's like a line of control yeah
between the Greek held Island uh parts
of the island which is Southern Cyprus
and the Turkish held part which is
Northern Cyprus and turkey has a
military presence on Cyprus there is a
significant Turkish military presence on
Cyprus yeah
and the Americans have had a policy for
the past 30 40 35 years or so to not
interfere in this dispute
yeah and the Americans had an arms
embargo on Cyprus which means that they
had a policy of not selling any arms to
Cyprus which means the Greek Cyprus and
now what's happened they have changed
that policy they have decided to lift
the Cyprus arms embargo
which means they are arming the Greek
held portion of the island against the
Turkish held portion of the island so if
there are tensions Rising who is
creating the rising of the tensions
it's the U.S
now we don't understand why they're
doing this as well so this is one thing
yeah
so they have the Americans have fully
lifted the weapons are embargo on the
divided island of Cyprus starting in
2023 what the Turks said it would start
an arms race and so on uh
so they are selling various uh weapons
and so on the Americans are let's see
what is written here let's take a look
at a different article to understand
what we Americans are arming the
cypriots with
yeah this is an example of the Weaponry
that the Americans are selling to Cyprus
Greece receives more more m117 Guardian
armored safety vehicles from the U.S
so uh
the U.S government plans to supply more
than around around 1 200 armored
vehicles to Greece by the end of this
year 2022 and so on
so that will bolster
uh the Greek military and this I think
is in Greece
so understand this
the Americans are sending arms to Cyprus
the Greek held portion of Cyprus it's uh
they're arming it against the Turkish
held portion of Cyprus and they are also
sending significant supplies large
supplies of of these armored vehicles to
the to Mainland Greece itself
yeah so the Americans are strengthening
the Greek military and the Greek
military capabilities and the only enemy
Greek Greece has is Turkey
that's what's happening that is what is
causing these tensions to rise let's
let's see some more let me put that
article back on the screen
uh
is this the article or is it a different
article I should see let's see let's see
the previous one
uh let's see
where the Americans are
okay let's see this third article let me
let me put a different article a third
article
here we are
so uh
this is a this is an article in in uh
maybe a Turkish publication right
and uh
the Americans are saying that they are
arming Greece is a precaution against
Russian activities
that's what the Americans Americans are
saying and there is this this place
called aleksandro Puli Port which is
very close to the Turkish border where
there is a significant uh you know
influx of American weapons
and uh there is a significant
militarization of this port done by The
Americans
uh the Americans say it is it is aimed
at Russia this place received 14 times
more military supplies from the US in
2021 than in previous years a dramatic
increase that cannot be solely explained
by the Ukraine war the Americans are
also providing Greece with F-35 fighter
planes and they have refused to provide
those fighter planes to Turkey
they refuse to provide those fighter
planes
to Turkey so these are the kind of
things that are happening so it is
American activities that are
exacerbating and creating these tensions
between turkey
and Greece yes
and so that's why Mr erdogan is is so
unhappy that's why he's all riled up and
that's why he's making threats to Greece
that remember your place in history
remember remember the past what we have
done to you and we could come and invade
you one night it could happen
so it is a statement that is making
against Greece and also against the
Americans who are arming Greece
now why is the United States arming
Greece
the United States is arming Greece and
the lag begins foreign
the U.S is arming Greece
against turkey and also to some extent
against Russia
if you see the map
then Greece is not really that far
from Russia
Greece is a major Nation on the agency
and it is the sea that connects the
Black Sea
with the Mediterranean Sea and the
Russia is not very very far off and
Greece also had various tensions in the
past with Russia
so the Americans are using that as an
excuse to arm Greece
um we also know that the Turks have in
the past uh bought Weapons Systems from
Russia including uh the s-400
anti-missile system
so uh
and because the Turks bought this this s
400 system from the Russians that's why
the Americans refused to sell the F-35
fighter plane to Turkey so there are
tensions between the U.S and turkey and
the fact that the Americans are arming
Greece is a continuation of these
tension intentions
so it's it's a message that they are
sending to Turkey
and we also have to remember that there
are a number of U.S nuclear weapons on
Turkish soil and these nuclear weapons
are aimed at Russia so it is a very
complicated situation that we are in
it's a complicated situation
but turkey is slowly moving eastwards
turkey
see Mr erdogan has Imperial Ambitions he
essentially wants to recreate the
Ottoman Empire yes uh he has already
tried to invade Syria there are portions
of Syria that are that are occupied
small portions of Syria that are
occupied by Turkish troops or have been
in the past turkey was closely aligned
with Isis during the Isis disaster in
the Middle East well Isis is a whole
different story but that that is that
was there yeah and turkey has Imperial
Ambitions of its own it wants to become
an Empire of in its own right it wants
to assume the the Global Leadership of
the Islamic world
which will bring it into conflict with
the US its Ambitions are not compatible
with U.S Ambitions yeah so it is natural
for the for turkey to slowly drift away
from from NATO but
since we have U.S nuclear weapons on
Turkish territory it means you have
nuclear U.S
armed Personnel also on Turkish
territory which complicates the
situation
and yet turkey is nowadays threatening
Greece with war it could actually happen
the Turks May some at some point in time
decide to attack Greece which would be a
very dangerous thing for them to do
because the Americans are in a position
to destroy if the Turks do that so
that's what it is so they so everything
is not well in NATO uh most likely we
will not see a war between Greece and
Turkey anytime soon but the tensions
exist and the tensions are getting worse
it's the Americans who are making the
tensions worse it's also the and it's
also the reason for that is also because
turkey has its own Ambitions it it does
not want to stay an obedient was all of
the U.S it also wants to become a major
player in the world so all these big and
all of this is caused by the visible
gradual decline of U.S hegemony
worldwide the US is now perceived to be
a declining power which is why turkey is
rising raising its head and saying that
I have my own Ambitions and I will do
things and I will not obey all the
dictates of the US and that's what the
Saudis are also doing and various other
nations will now feel like doing that as
well the Germans are unhappy the Germans
are unhappy because they can no longer
acquire a Russian gas which they were
getting for so cheap Nordstrom has been
destroyed I know I think we know who did
that right and so on
so it's a complicated situation who's
funding turkey most likely there are
well the Turks have their own economy of
course they they have weapons that they
sell to the world and obviously there
are funds coming in when it comes to
Saudi Arabia turkey and Saudi Arabia
don't have the best relationship just
like Saudi Arabia and Iran don't have
the best relationship Saudi Arabia and
turkey don't have the best relationship
because both are major powers and turkey
has Imperial ambitions
Saudi Arabia is seen is perceived to be
globally from from the world's
perspective to be the home of Islam
because the two holiest sites of Islam
Mecca and Madina are in Saudi Arabia
turkey doesn't like this turkey wants to
reclaim the position of the great leader
of the of the Islamic world
the the the the great Khalif the
caliphate right uh the last caliphate
was the Ottoman caliphate based out of
Constantinople Istanbul they would like
that position they would like to reclaim
the position but right now Saudi Arabia
has the position so that's why there is
this rivalry between Saudi Arabia and
turkey and so on and so forth yeah so
that is the complicated situation where
we are in right now I personally don't
see a war breaking out anytime very soon
because if the Turks attack Greece the
Americans will defend Greece and they
the the Americans will not tolerate that
sort of uh that sort of action by one of
their one of the Nations they considered
to be their was all state
so yeah very complicated situation
intentions are rising within within NATO
and there's this
her says hush asks after the Turks the
Turks have accused USA of Bomb Blast and
them not allowing Finland and Sweden
into NATO
can you guys think of kicking turkey out
of NATO
what changes can be expected to be made
in foreign policy by against turkey by
India okay okay let's let's address the
bigger thing that's a good question
right
so recently there was this Bomb Blast
very unfortunate in in Istanbul in in
Constantinople Istanbul in one of the
major crowded marketplaces or tourist
spots or whatever and I'm not sure how
many people lost their lives very
unfortunate but that's what happened it
was a suicide bomb
and uh the Turks were able to capture at
least one person a lady
a female uh who whom they were accused
of being one of the people involved in
this terrorist attack
and they say that this person who they
have captured was a member of the pkk
it's a Kurdish uh Rebel
uh Armed Force or whatever you know they
they wish to liberate Kurdistan from
Turkish clutches
so if you look at the map what is
Kurdistan
Kurdistan is a is a state that doesn't
exist the region between turkey uh
Eastern Turkey
North Western Iran
and so in Northern parts of Iraq and
Syria are the homelands of the Kurdish
people the Kurdish people are an
indo-iranian people okay they are all uh
converted to Islam now but their
language is not an is not Arabic it's
not a Semitic language it's in Iranian
language they say the Kurdish language
in their culture their old culture was
very different from the Arabic or
somatic culture so the Kurds and one of
their the one of the major Islamic
historical figures
was occurred he was born in tikrit in
Northern Iraq yes
if I'm not mistaken it was decreed which
is also the whole the both place or or
hometown of Saddam Hussein anyhow that's
that's I'm digressing so Kurdistan is
this region which uh which is divided
between multiple Nations between turkey
between Iran between Iraq and parts of
Syria as well the yazidis also live in
some in parts of in some of these
territories so
the Kurds have been fighting for a very
long time for decades if not centuries
for a homeland of their own a
nation-state of their own right now the
territory is divided up between
different nations and they all are
persecuted in all these different
different nations the Iranians persecute
the Kurds the Turks persecute the Kurds
so do I would
I would expect
um okay I'll talk about only Iran and
turkey I'll not talk about Iraq and
Syria so there is Kurdish persecution in
Iran as well as in Turkey they have been
fighting what they call a freedom fight
their freedom fighters in Turkey there's
an organization called the pkk and the
Turks have said that this person who was
arrested by them in connection with the
Bomb Blast that happened recently was a
member of pkk now pkk is an organization
that the Turks say has been funded by
the United States so when the U.S
officially
uh sent a message of condolence to the
Turks to Turkey in response to the Bomb
Blast the Turks rejected the American
condolences officially
yeah so they are indirectly accusing the
Americans of having a hand in this
terrorist attack in Constantinople in
Istanbul
so once again you are seeing increasing
tensions between turkey and the United
States
and of course like uh harsh has pointed
out the Turks have been refusing
to allow Finland and Sweden to join NATO
so Finland I think has made the
application to join NATO I'm not sure
about Sweden but yeah NATO wants to
expand but the thing is that uh it has
to be uh Any Nation when it applies to
join NATO all the member states of NATO
have to agree to this unanimously
that's the deal
and turkey is refusing to accept this
and the Americans obviously would want
Finland and Sweden and whoever else to
join NATO
so yeah more tensions between the U.S
and turkey
so the Americans in response to all
these activities by turkey are arming
Greece
they've started arming Greece they've
started arming Cyprus and this is all
aimed at Turkey if you arm Greece Greece
has only one major enemy nation which is
turkey if you arm Southern Cyprus that
is aimed at Northern Cyprus which is
occupied currently by turkey
so these are all actions that are
hostile to Turkey these are all actions
that negatively affect turkeys National
Security
same like America Army Pakistan which
can only be aimed at India similar to
that right
so there are all these tensions
happening between the U.S and turkey
so the question is what changes can be
expected uh
will the U.S think of kicking turkey out
of NATO the U.S I don't think will
think of kicking turkey out of NATO they
will think of squeezing and pressurizing
turkey more because turkey is a very
well valuable piece of territory it's a
great territory if you want to contain
Russia the Turks would like to make
things better to to see turkey Russia
relations get better they obviously
bought the S 400 missile system from
Russia
which was very much something that
displeased the Americans and that's why
the Americans refused to sell the F-35
fighter plane to Turkey
so turkey is trying to align with Russia
to a certain extent and the Americans
will do their best to prevent this from
happening so they will not give up on
Turkey they will keep turkey a member of
NATO and they will pressurize it more
and more they will use every means at
the disposal every liver that they have
in their hand at the disposal to
pressurize turkey and make turkey
succeed to their demands and make turkey
behave that's what I see happening so I
think tensions will rise between the U.S
and turkey let's say they expel turkey
from NATO then the very strategic
traits the Turkish Straits will no
longer be under U.S control the Strait
of the Dardanelles and the Strait of
Bosphorus
these two states are incredibly
important from a geostrategic
perspective because they are two choke
points that connect the Black Sea with
the Mediterranean two two stroke wounds
not one
yeah so any Russian
activity in this region Naval activity
has to pass through
these streets so if the Russians are
sending let's say a submarine or an
aircraft carrier or a destroyer to the
Mediterranean Sea from the Black Sea
Fleet it will have to pass through these
traits so
and and the rule is that these these
vessels have to be completely visible
and above the surface of the water
when they pass through
this region so the Americans if they
control these two states traits these
two choke points they have an incredible
amount of control and leverage and
advantage in this region which is why
they cannot afford to let turkey slip
out of NATO
and of course they have U.S military
personnel on Turkish territory and U.S
nuclear weapons on Turkish territory
which are aimed at Russia so they have
their claws deep inside turkey and I
don't see them wishing to let Turkey
leave NATO yeah
so yeah that is the game that is being
played in nato in Europe
uh what changes can be expected to be
made in foreign policy against turkey by
India
India will try and ensure that India
Turkish India turkey relations will
remain at a reasonably even kill no
major tensions yeah the Turks keep on
making this noise of supporting Pakistan
and all that but they have their own
natural interest in mind they have their
own problems to solve in their own
geographical region uh whatever support
they are doing for Pakistan is more like
lip service they've like I said They
wish to take on the mantle of the leader
of the Islamic world and one of the ways
of doing it is is to support a nation
like Pakistan
uh if they are actually arming Pakistan
in some way that would be a whole
different thing so India and turkey we
have never had very good relations yeah
and I don't see relations becoming great
in the future but India I'm sure will
try to make sure that relations don't
deteriorate too much
so I don't see turkey being a very major
factor in Indian foreign policy it is
obviously an important nation in Europe
in the Middle East region in the
Mediterranean region so India has to
keep an eye on the on whatever is
happening with turkey
but I don't see any major shift in
foreign policy from India's perspective
Visa with turkey happening anytime soon
unless something drastic happens which
most likely you won't
in the near future
Gotham says I've heard you talk about
how Pakistan will eventually return to
India my question is do we really need
Pakistan or should we just focus on the
Pok region only so that transit to
Central Asia becomes easy how will
Pakistan with such a radicalized society
and a strong hate towards Indian culture
reunite with India amicably good
question
let's go to the map because that will
help us understand the situation
uh so yes I have said this multiple
times that Pakistan will eventually
return to India when I mean when I say
eventually I mean we're talking about a
hundred year Horizon it's not going to
happen next week next month next year
next 10 years
we would like to first see Pakistan the
the the Pakistani army to be removed as
a factor from this region and the ideal
situation is that without any Warfare
without any violence uh sin should be
allowed to become free below to become
free uh Pakistani Punjab can become free
and and the Pashto Islam region should
maybe reunite with Afghanistan that's
the ideal situation and then slowly we
can think of in the long long
term reunite Pakistan these various
parts of Pakistan with India because
this is Indian Territory it has been
Indian Territory for territory for at
least 10 000 years it is an integral
part of India's cultural and
civilizational Ethos in our territory it
is our heritage that has been stolen
from us this territorial Heritage the
Indus River is an integral part of India
India is incomplete without sindhudesh
without the Sindhu River without all
these regions which have been part of
our territory historically
and so on so forth So eventually it will
reunite with India it's not going to
happen soon
it cannot happen soon like like Gotham
is saying the Pakistani Society is
deeply deeply radicalized and they have
this this deep hatred for Indian culture
it doesn't make sense to reunite in
these regions of Pakistan with India
even if Pakistan breaks up in the future
it doesn't make sense it's gonna cause
huge problems for them and for us as
well we don't want that
the question is do we really need
Pakistan we do we need to reunite
reunify India with these uh territories
that were excised from India by the
British we do need to do it in the long
term over a hundred year Horizon because
these are our ancestral territories
this is our heritage we cannot just let
it go it is
it is not right to let it go it is part
of it is an integral part of India it
will be reunified when the time is right
so yes we do need we do need Pakistan
but not yet not yet and not now
right now like Gotham says we should
focus on the Pok region foreign
we need to focus on that because through
the because when we reacquire pojk and
Pakistan we will once again have a
direct land root with Afghanistan and
through Afghanistan we will be able to
first of all help the people of
Afghanistan help them out and also have
a clear open route to Central Asia and
to Europe through Afghanistan yes so
that's why any immediate the immediate
focus should be let's say in the next 10
years on reacquiring pojk Pakistan
occupied jamun Kashmir including and
maybe some other parts of Pakistan
whatever whatever we need because this
region the wahan corridor region is very
highly mountainous it's not feasible
it's not very easy to build railway
lines or roads through the through that
region so maybe we can also acquire some
other territory that is temporarily part
of Pakistan you know closer to uh
Mainland Afghanistan and so on
so initially we need to focus in the
immediate future next 10 years hopefully
on reacquiring pojk that means to become
part of to be reunified with India at
the earliest that way we will be able to
have a direct land route to Afghanistan
and through Afghanistan to Central Asia
and Europe that will be great that's
what India has been cut off from that
was the reason reason why the British
supported Pakistan in their uh attempt
to to capture Kashmir
to cut India off from Central Asia India
has always had these long trade routes
and connections with Central Asia and
for the past 70 years we've been
deprived of that so the first thing is
to recapture reunify pojk and in the
long run over 100 or so year Horizon we
will reintegrate Pakistan with the
motherland India right
Daniel Nicholson says harboring
superpower Ambitions demands
geopolitical assertion that sees no
right or wrong correct there's no right
or wrong in geopolitics India's
neighbors are more nuisance and help for
us do you think our Ambitions could get
a shot in the arm if we are next
neighboring Nations that went against us
once we become a double digit trillion
dollar economy means a 10 trillion
dollar economy that would also
effectively convey a message to less
than friendly Nations to not mess with
India thank you look you cannot learn
how to sprint before you learn how to
walk so the first order of business is
to reach the 10 trillion dollar Mark GDP
yeah once you do that I do not see any
need to Annex neighboring Nations let's
look at the geography of the Indian
subcontinent which are the Nations that
are part that have historically been
part of India we have Pakistan
Afghanistan yes Nepal
um Bangladesh Bangladesh Sri Lanka the
Maldives
and yeah databouts yep
so the question is will our superpower
Ambitions get a shot in the arm if we
Annex neighboring Nations does India
have superpower Ambitions what is a
superpower how do you define a
superpower here's how I Define
superpower in my definition a superpower
is a nation that has control more or
less over the entire world and the
nation that can intervene militarily
anywhere in the world at 30 to 60
minutes notice does India want to be
that sort of nation a global hegemon
I don't think India wants to be a Global
hegeman India should obviously be the
major uh most powerful economy in the
world which has always been the
historical position of India
historically India has always been the
number one economy in the world India
needs to regain that status of the
greatest largest economy in the world
and if you are the largest economy in
the world you need the means to be able
to protect and safeguard that which
means India needs to have a massive
military that is proportional to its
economic might and if India becomes the
biggest economy in the world then India
should also be the biggest military in
the world but that doesn't mean
so if if you do that then India will
have to secure Supply chains and trade
routes and all that which means that
India will have to expand its military
footprint especially in other ways India
will have to have a much larger Air
Force much larger Navy to safeguard all
those Supply chains trade routes in in
other nations as Nations that Supply
materials and all those things so
India's economic and Military in Naval
and Air Force footprint will need to
grow
proportionate to its economy but that
doesn't require a nexing neighboring
Nations let's talk about let's say Sri
Lanka
will India need to Annex Sri Lanka in
the future I don't think so
I don't think so Sri Lanka is anywhere
friendly neighboring Nation we have more
or less the same culture same everything
just like Nepal why can't we have the
kind of relationship we have with Nepal
we don't need to Annex Nepal we have an
open border with Nepal the people of
Nepal have the right to come to India
and live in India as long as they want
and work in India as long as they want
they essentially have almost the same
rights as Indian citizens and vice versa
the only thing is that the Nepalese
cannot vote in Indian elections but the
Nepali Nepalese people have the right to
serve in the Indian Armed Forces because
we see Nepal as the same people as us
and the same Nation more or less the
same people the same Heritage as us we
could have a similar relationship with
Sri Lanka why not without having to
actually Annex the nation so we could
create
like like they have the EU with open
borders they could create a
subcontinental union similar to that and
maybe expanded Beyond two other friendly
Nations maybe in the future we could add
Myanmar in Thailand and Laos in Cambodia
in Vietnam to that maybe even in
Indonesia and so on we can think of it
in that manner so without actually
annexing other nations we can integrate
that those nations with our economy and
have more or less open borders with
friendly Nations
hopefully even westwards in the future
hopefully in the next hundred years even
with with what is now Pakistan what is
now Afghanistan and maybe even with our
our real neighbors the the parses the
Iranians we could have that once things
are better in the world yeah
so I would say India needs to raise its
economic might India needs to maybe in
the next 50 years become the world's
largest economy which will need which
will necessitate India to have the
world's largest military and most
powerful military as well and we can use
that military for good instead of using
it for bullying and bullying other
nations and creating vasal States we can
use it for actual good
for actual good in the world that's what
India has always been India has always
been a force of good rather than evil
India has never been a colonizer India
has always given more than it has taken
it has never taken anything from the
Nations so that's what India should
aspire to be instead of becoming a new
bully like the Americans like like the
Anglo-Saxon Empire Saxon Empire or like
like what the Chinese wish to be we
could be a force for good but be the
largest force in the world
so that's how I see
our future foreign policy once we become
a significant military and economic
power that's the kind of superpower
India should
aim to be not a hegemen but a Force for
good
chiching says why was Delhi chosen as
the capital of India what were the
reasons behind that this is a great
question I'm uh yeah nobody's asked this
thus far very good question so yes
India's capital city is Delhi now
if you go back
deep in India's history like really deep
not very deep but it's not reasonably
deep
go back to the time of the Mahabharata
the capital of the pandavas was called
and there was another major city called
indraprasth well in the Press is the
site of me of present-day Delhi so
indrapras there is this this region this
part of Delhi which is called Indra path
which is the
geographical site of the historical
indraprasth from the Mahabharata days
so so
it's a very old place first of all Delhi
and it's always been very significant uh
later on during the Tomar Dynasty Delhi
Delhi was the capital of the Tomar
rajputs if I'm not mistaken it was also
the capital of prithvira Johan
um was it it was always a major uh City
it was from time to time uh one of the
major cities and one of the centers of
power in India the last Indian Emperor
who was crowned in when I say Indian I
mean
a person who
uh followed Indian culture and
traditions the last Hindu Emperor so to
say was crowned emperor in Delhi there
was
his army was entirely like 90 of his
office soldiers were pashtoons but he
was crowned the Emperor of India which
included Afghanistan by the way at the
time in Delhi so Delhi has from time to
time been a major major city and from
time to time being the capital of India
yeah
during the time of let's say
chandragupta maurya during the mauryan
era when the modern Empire uh had
unified the subcontinent at that time
the capital of India was partly Putra
which is currently called Patna yeah
and even during the Gupta era when the
Gupta Empire had again reunified India
the capital of India was partly Putra
Patna during the kushan era we had two
capitals one was I think mathura one was
a purushpur Peshawar yeah during
kanishka's time so India has had various
capitals from time to time when the
British annexed I mean when the British
occupied India their Capital was Kolkata
in the far not in the Far East of India
but to the east yeah at the time of what
is now Bangladesh was also part of India
so their Capital was Kolkata
but then they expanded out of Bengal and
they were able to capture more or less
all of India yes uh and then they they
realized that their capital city is in
the east of India it should be a more
centralized location which is why I
think it was in 1931 that they made
Delhi the capital of India and they
constructed a newer newer part of the
city which they called New Delhi and
that's why they they made this more
centrally located uh City
or the capital of the of British India
at the time it was centrally located
because what is now Pakistan was also
part of India at the time it was
undivided India it was not partition
India so Delhi was more or less to some
extent in the center ideally you want a
city in madhya Pradesh or something yeah
but yeah so so that's what they did so
that is the main reason
why Delhi was chosen as the capital of
India and the the British has also
partitioned Bengal into East Bengal and
West Bengal along religious lines and
there were all these religious conflicts
and riots and all things tensions in in
Bengal in Calcutta that's why they
wanted to leave the place and leave and
come to Delhi yeah so these are the
reasons why they made Delhi the capital
of British India and after India's
so-called Independence uh the people who
came the people to whom power was
transferred were all anglophiles and
they believed in continuing whatever the
British had done in India so they
changed nothing and Delhi remained the
capital of India maybe in the future
we should think of of a new capital
maybe a brand new capital somewhere in
real Central India or maybe going back
to maybe let's say partly Putra or maybe
to peshav or purushpur or maybe mathura
we've had many great cities in the past
maybe Pune Pune was a was the capital
was the capital of India during the
maratha Empire time you know so there
have been many various cities that in
the past have served that have served as
the capital of India in Delhi is just
one of them there's nothing apart from
that really special some people you know
what they say this they said that Delhi
has a very bad history it's a it is a
cursed City some people say
from the days of the Mahabharata itself
and obviously this this like it's a city
that brings bad luck uh when the the the
the Barbarian Timur
invaded India he he conducted a horrific
massacre in in Delhi in which at least a
hundred thousand innocent men women and
children were butchered in just one day
in the streets of Delhi the city was
Awash in blood so it's got a very bad
very dark history the city and some
people say it's not appropriate for a
city like that to be the capital of
India maybe maybe they're right I don't
know I I would say that maybe and you
know
so there are many reasons for which
which
would justify
India getting a new capital city maybe
somewhere in the actual Center of India
but yeah that's for the political class
to decide
but I think that explains why Delhi was
Capital was chosen as the capital of
India it's a very good question
says recently the prime minister of
India said about Indonesia that
Indonesia is currently 90 nautical miles
from India I think they watch they watch
a show and I I don't know about that
anyway so what's what's my take on our
neighborhood status of Indonesia
Thailand Malaysia why don't we consider
them as neighbors but we consider
Maldives to be our neighbor
let's take a look at the map yeah
so the Prime Minister said that
Indonesia is about roughly 90 nautical
miles from India this is the island of
great nicobar right which is India's
southernmost uh territory and over here
you have sabang and you have Banda let's
see the distance between uh the great
nicobar Island
and the northern tip of Indonesia that's
176 kilometers you divide that by two
it's about eight yeah it's it's a
roughly note 90 or so nautical miles
yeah so Indonesia is is less than 200
kilometers from India and yet nobody in
India thinks of Indonesia as a neighbor
there is something called a maritime
neighbor see Sri Lanka obviously doesn't
currently have a land connection with
India in the past we did we had the
great Rama setu today there is of the
parks trade the Gulf of Mana the Park
Street which uh lies between Mainland
India and Mainland Sri Lanka so Sri
Lanka is currently not connected with
India and yet we think of Sri Lanka as
our neighboring country it's a maritime
neighbor just the same way
Indonesia is also very much a maritime
neighbor of India and similarly so is
Thailand
most of Thailand is over here but some
of it is over here let's say the uh the
the the resort island of Phuket how far
is it from uh great nicobar island of
India let's see from here to here let's
measure the distance
it's about
um it's about four it's about 500
kilometers so it's about 500 kilometers
from India across the Andaman sea so why
is it not considered to be a neighboring
country of India I consider Thailand to
be a neighboring country of India
I but that's not how the way that's not
the way we are taught geography when you
go to school you learn geography they
give you a set of Nations that you have
to memorize as India's Neighbors The
First Nation they teach you is Pakistan
so that's why nobody and people are not
taught how to think
critical thinking yeah and that's why
nobody in India thinks of Thailand as a
neighboring Nation or Indonesia as a
neighboring Nation even though they are
so from my perspective India has a
number of nations that are our neighbors
with the from the perspective of land
borders Tibet is what Nepal is one
Bhutan is one Bangladesh Myanmar
and we have Afghanistan Pakistan
temporarily uh actually Iran should be
our neighbor once Pakistan is
reintegrated and then we have Maritime
neighbors Maldives over here obviously
which is really far from the coastline
of India and yet we consider it to be a
neighbor so Maldives is one
the Seychelles is another one which is
not really far away
um I would also consider Eastern Africa
to be our neighbor Somalia and Oman and
Yemen and of course these nations
um Malaysia Indonesia and Thailand
so from my perspective these are all our
neighboring Nations we have a number of
Maritime neighbors that we don't think
about
so the reason why most Indians don't
consider them neighbors is because it's
not taught that way in our geography
textbooks when we are in school that's
why we don't think about it yeah but
these are actually our neighbors
Mona Lisa says
could you tell us please why Ukraine and
Belarus became two founding members of
the United Nations in 1945 even though
they were not independent nations at the
time in 1945 they were part of the USSR
until 1991. why how did this happen what
an interesting question good question
Mona Lisa so here's what happened the
United Nations was formed in 1945 at
that time you had the USSR which had I
don't know how many 26 27 Nations oh
sorry republics so the USSR stands for
Union of Soviet Socialist republics so
all of these
republics Soviet Socialist Republicans
like Ukraine like Belarus
Pakistan like and so on and so forth
these were all various republics that
were that were constituent members of
the USSR
in 1945
there was something called the British
Commonwealth India was part of that
India you know India was still part of
the British Empire at the time it was
still
for illegally occupied by Britain but
you had Nations like Australia which was
also which was also owned by the British
crown like New Zealand which was also
owned by the British crown like Canada
which was also owned by the British
crown it is still actually owned by the
British crown so these were all members
of the Commonwealth the the UK's
Commonwealth
so the UK wanted these nations to be
individual members independent members
of the United Nations even though they
were actually all ruled from London yeah
so Stalin said that this is wrong
how can you do this you are ruling all
these territories from London so why
don't you have just one seat in the U.N
for the for the entire British Empire
why are you you know so if you if you
even though you are ruling it all from
one place but you are giving more seats
in the U.N to these territories it means
you get more votes for yourself
so by doing it that way the Western
Powers the English-speaking Powers were
getting more votes in the U.N so they
could influence the decisions and
proceedings in the U.N because they had
more seats more votes so Stalin said
that if you are doing it this way then
every single Republic of the USSR should
get its own vote in the U.N
when he said that the Americans said
that in that case we want each American
state 50 states to have a separate seat
in the U.N so there was this squabbling
that was going on so as a compromise
it was decided that the USSR
will get two additional seats in the U.N
which is the Ukraine FSR SSR in the
Belarus SSR even though Ukraine and
Belarus was were part of the USSR
so so USSR got three seats and three
votes
in the U.N in the United Nations but it
got only one seat in the U.N security
Council the permanent five the top five
which is understood to be understood
which is understandable so that's how it
happened that's how Ukraine and Belarus
even though they were part of the USSR
got became became two separate founding
members of the UN interesting very
interesting story
foreign
states of the US like Japan Germany Etc
are rich While others like Pakistan are
poor is it in the interest of the US to
keep these countries rich or poor or is
it because of the leadership
okay
why is it so why are some Nations Rich
why are some Nations poor
so Japan was destroyed at the end of the
second World War by 1945 Japan had been
nuked twice it was totally destroyed
totally flattened bombed to the ground
then the Americans Occupied Japan and
under American occupation the Japanese
were allowed to rise again and because
of the industriousness and all that of
the Japanese people the hard work and
all that they were able to make Japan a
major economy once again it had become
the second largest economy in the world
in the 1980s and it could have actually
surpassed the United States
and then some things were done in
Japan's economy was destroyed it's still
a major Nation a very rich and
prosperous Nation so Japan was under U.S
occupation South Korea also was
underwent the same process it was under
U.S occupation it was also allowed to
rise and become prosperous
Germany Etc were all rebuilt after the
destruction of the second world war
under U.S stewardship Germany like Japan
and South Korea is also under U.S
permanent occupation
okay and the Americans allowed Germany
to become a major industrial power again
it became the PowerHouse of Europe and
it was all beneficial to the Americans
because the Americans actually occupied
Western Europe and controlled Western
Europe
and obviously you have the NATO Nations
and all that so Europe had a high degree
of prosperity because they had looted
and pillaged and plundered the entire
world for 500 years before the second
world war Africa and India obviously the
the UK obviously had a plundered India
for centuries
so the the European nations produce very
little compared to to nations in Africa
and Asia and yet they became so
prosperous it's because they stole all
the wealth out of the rest of the world
that's why they were prosperous
and that those riches still
um most of those riches and all that
wealth still persisted after the second
world war that's why these nations the
European nations were Rich Japan rebuilt
itself South Korea rebuilt itself after
the after the Korean War Europe was
already rich so that's why these basal
States in Europe were already rich
and that's how Japan and South Korea
were allowed to become rich Pakistan is
a vasal state but the U.S has never
occupied Pakistan
they have put a puppet power the the
they have propped up the the dictatorial
regime of the Pakistani army and the isi
the U.S has never
never actually physically occupied
Pakistan
so Pakistan is a client State it's a
Basalt stage it's like it's like many
African dictatorships that are also U.S
clients States or basal States but the
US doesn't actually occupy those Nations
yeah
so that's why some client states or
visal states are rich and some are poor
it's not like the U.S decides that these
nations will be allowed to become rich
and these will be kept War it's not like
that they just use whatever is there
available to them to their benefit and
that's how
it is done
and I had so many other questions that I
had to take
but I think we we have we are reaching
the end of today's session let me see if
I can take one or two more
how dangerous are solar flares how
severely can they impact life on Earth
okay let's talk about solar flares first
so solar flare so the sun is a star it's
a ball of fluid it's a ball of gas but
that gas is very dense uh the density of
the hydrogen gas on the sun is is it's
it's it's thicker than water it's denser
than water yeah and the Sun is a highly
magnetized saw there are this massive
enormously powerful magnetic fields that
lie below the surface of the Sun and the
sun has this this uh has an atmosphere
the Corona and all that and these
magnetic fields they create these Loops
you know the magnetic lines of force you
can see these loops on the in the
atmosphere of the Sun and these Loops
are always changing they're always
interacting with each other and
sometimes the break
and if this happens in the atmosphere of
the sun it it uh the sun is always
ejecting the solar wind which causes
auroras on Earth but when one of these
solar one of these magnetic lines of
force breaks off
it it gives us what's called a coronal
mass ejection which is a huge Outburst
of plasma from the sun's surface and if
it comes in the direction of this of the
earth then it can cause something like
the Carrington event which is an event
that happened I think in 1859
so it was this huge coronal mass
ejection that hit the earth
it impacted the Earth's magnetic field
so when something like this hits the
Earth there is no real effect of on life
on Earth it doesn't affect us because
most of it is absorbed by the magnetic
field of the earth and the atmosphere
none of these uh none of this plasma is
able to actually Reach This surface of
the Earth but you see intense uh
magnetic activity in the form of these
auroras so in the when the current and
event happened it was the most powerful
and this thing is called geomagnetic
storm so it was the most powerful
geomagnetic storm ever recorded yeah you
had auroras along the Equator if I'm not
mistaken typically you see auroras along
the poles the North Pole and the South
Pole of the Earth but this was so
intense that auroras were witnessed near
the equator of the Earth
and various uh Telegraph systems they
started sparking in the fires and all
that because of induced currents that
are induced by magnetism and all that so
these solar flares and geomagnetic
storms and events like the current event
they don't they will not cause any
actual loss of life or or or any damage
to anyone's Health but they can destroy
electrical grids totally destroy
electrical grids so they could knock off
electrical grids across the world if
something like this happens again
and your laptops and whatever else you
use will get fried destroyed and to
replace those burnt out destroyed
Electric electrical grids could take
months perhaps years in cold places
people could die from exposure to Coal
because there is no electricity
available for heating and so on and it
could destroy satellites around the
earth it could destroy hundreds of
satellites we would be left without any
Communications that thing
will happen one of these days it's the
statistical certainty
so yeah so solar flares are dangerous
from that perspective they cannot kill
anybody or affect life on Earth or make
anybody sick but they can destroy our
electrical infrastructure they could
destroy our Communications
infrastructure they could destroy
satellites and they could destroy all
kinds of equipment on the earth which
could be a disaster which would destroy
economies worldwide and it could
actually kill people from exposure to
cold in cold places so that's why solar
flares and geomagnetic storms and
coronal mass ejections are potentially
very dangerous
all right let me take a couple of
questions from the live chat I had many
questions that I had in queue but let's
take some questions from the live chat
right now yes
and Manufacturing and Logistics and much
more absolutely right yes
okay bhavesh says Coco Islands issue
China is constructing an airstrip on one
of the islands so the cocoa islands are
two islands in the very North part of
the andamans let's take a look at it
I'm sure you all know where the Andaman
Islands are so to the north of the
Andaman Islands you have these two cocoa
Islands which belong to India but the
great magnificent prime minister of
India SRI SRI jawaharlal nehruji gifted
them to Burma for whatever reason for
reasons known best to him so the the
thing is is China constructing an island
sorry an airstrip on one of these
islands let us see
satellite
do we have satellite satellite yes let's
see the satellite image
let's close that so there are two Coco
Islands the South one has just forests
it's very small it's about a kilometer
or so in in length the northern island
has an airstrip
it's been around for a long time this
airstrip
and it's got all kinds of infrastructure
also
it's it's a very well organized as you
can see there are residential buildings
there are buildings that look like
offices there is this building which
could be a hangar perhaps possibly we
don't know
there are the buildings here there's a
whole complex in the north yeah
so there is a lot of infrastructure on
this island very well developed very
well organized and a significant
airstrip let's see how long it is
measure distance from Top from bottom to
the top
it's 2.4 kilometers let's say two
kilometers that is a very significant
airstrip you can land heavy military
planes on this island
so
this infrastructure
is has been constructed by the by the
Chinese the Burmese many years ago
decades ago perhaps handed over this
island to the Chinese and the Chinese
have developed all this infrastructure
on this island some of it is military in
nature some of it
this essentially is a signals
intelligence gathering station they use
this this this place
uh where is it
go back to default yeah so they use this
island to eavesdrop on Indian Naval and
military activity in the andamans and in
the larger Indian Ocean region in the
Bay of Bengal region yeah in the Kalinga
mahasagar region
so that's that's what's happening so the
Chinese are not building an airstrip on
the island they have already done it
long ago and they use this this facility
this infrastructure for spying on India
that's what is going on and that is all
thanks to the magnificence and
generosity of the great Shri jawaharlal
nehruji the most magnificent prime
minister of India all right let's see
some other questions
let's see uh some other questions
uh how would chanakya have counted
terrorism well chanakya lived in a
different time and he was essentially
the most trusted advisor of the emperor
of India chandragupta maurya ruled over
large parts of India his rule was
unquestioned
so chanakya would have dealt with
terrorism with a very heavy hand with an
iron fist he would have smashed
terrorism those if he was in India today
in the 21st century his approach would
be different India is not a very major
majorly powerful Nation today India is
an emerging great power it's not a
superpower and there are lots of issues
in India internally and externally so
today chanakya would have advised the
more nuanced approach hide and bide hide
your capabilities bide your time and do
whatever you can stealthily yeah
all right yes sir somebody remembered
you
um
okay says why do you call Nations like
France and Germany vasals when America
has no Administration power over these
nations yes America does not administer
the nation these nations have elections
they have their own president they have
their own local government their own
City councils and all that everything is
them they have their own laws their own
legislature
so why do I call them vessels
because their foreign policy is dictated
by the U.S
they are members of NATO NATO is owned
by the US they are members of the EU the
EU is the pr front of NATO
EU and NATO are owned by the U.S they
are controlled by the U.S everything
that happens there is controlled by the
U.S the foreign policy and the economic
policy of these nations
is dictated by the U.S
France I I would say has a
quasi-independent foreign policy in the
sense that they have their own
independent military they have their own
nuclear warheads they have their own
submarines that are not controlled by
the Americans
yeah and they have nuclear warheads of
their own they have significant interest
in the Indian Ocean region but the core
foreign policy cannot deviate from U.S
national interests same goes for Germany
in the case of Germany do you uh do you
even hear me I said it a few minutes ago
Germany is under permanent U.S military
occupation it has been so since 1945.
there is permanent U.S military presence
in Germany military bases that are
controlled by the U.S that have U.S
military personnel on German territory
since 1945. the German Constitution was
written by Americans yeah technically it
was written by Germans but not a single
word
what is in the Constitution that was not
approved by the Americans and when
Germany was reunified it is the U.S
imposed Constitution that was extended
to Eastern Germany
these are the reasons why I say that
Nations like France and Germany and
every other Nation that's part of the EU
and every other Nation that's part
that's part of the of the NATO all these
nations are vasal states of the U.S yes
they make it look very nice to you there
are elections they have their own
presidents they have their own law they
have their own legislature and yet if
you look deep within if you peel back
some layers you will understand what's
really happening you have to dig a
Little Deeper do not look at things
superficially then you will understand
the world all right so that's the reason
why I always say that France in Germany
are vassals of the US
all right I will take one more question
um
let's see
okay let's take one question by Shaheen
to what extent to what extent can a
stellar fly by B stable as a solar
system is it conceivable that the Tobar
super explosion happened as a result of
the tidal forces from the Schultz star
a stellar flyby means another star
you know
the sun is is a star one of the billions
of stars
in the Milky Way galaxy
and the sun is not sitting in one place
it's moving around the center of the
Galaxy if the center of the Galaxy we
have this unseen object it's a
supermassive black hole it's sitting at
the center of the Galaxy it's holding
the entire galaxy together to a large
extent yeah it affects the it affects
the Dynamics of the Galaxy and the
movements of the Stars so all the stars
are doing this merry-go-round
around the Unseen Central supermassive
black hole of our galaxy and from time
to time stars come in close contact
Stars typically never Collide but star
systems can come in contact with each
other close to each other past near each
other that's called a stellar flyby
which means another star with its star
system with its planets and all that
comes close passes close by to the Sun
and about I don't know 80 000 or so
years ago there was a star called
Schultz star that that came very close
to the Sun it is a very small start but
it came very closely close to the Sun so
the question is how much can to what
extent can such a stellar fly by
destabilized solar system it's going to
have an effect if a massive object a
massive star
passes by the sun it's going to its
gravitational force gravitational pull
is going to reconfigure the solar system
if it comes too close otherwise it's
going to reorient some of the orbits of
the planets and asteroids and comets and
all that it can do that
so it's all about gravitation it's all
about gravity it's gravitational pull
will kind of perhaps change the
trajectory of the sun itself and it
could possibly end up changing certain
orbital configurations of the planets in
the solar system yeah so there have been
Community computer simulations done
about what effect the the
flyby of the Schultz star would have had
on
on the sun and the solar system and
maybe on the earth and the various uh
possibilities exist we're not quite sure
of how it went
um is it conceivable that the the Toba
super explosion super volcano explosion
occurred as a result of tidal forces I
think it's unlikely
our tidal forces will happen when you
have a gravitating object that's very
close to the to the Earth to the extent
that it deforms the surface and the
shape of the Earth
the moon does that but there is no other
object that comes so close even the sun
even the sun doesn't deform
the Earth's crust and surface to a
significant extent the sun does have
some effect on the tides on Earth but
not as much as the moon so you need to
be really close because gravity is a
very weak Force
so I don't think the Toba super volcano
explosion happened as a consequence of
the social star but yeah interesting
question
all right all right I think
I know lots of other questions I can do
it until tomorrow but I think we will
call it a day oh yeah it's been two
hours eight minutes so uh let me end the
session over here
thank you very much everybody uh yeah I
know there's a football match going on
the World Cup in Qatar wonderful watch
it
um yeah so that brings us to the end of
today's session to the end of episode
143 I hope you enjoyed it thank you very
much for all your questions thank you
very much for your viewership I really
appreciate it and we will continue this
next week until then take care
stay healthy take care and I'll see you
soon bye